Preliminary Inventory of the Wolfgang Janisch papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wolfgang Janisch papers
1924-2009
2000C90
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes, 13 oversize boxes, 2 cubic foot boxes, 4 linear feet (19.6 linear feet)
Memoirs, photographic collages, other photographs, postcards, correspondence, police reports, printed matter, sound recordings, videocassettes, and memorabilia relating to political dissent and the peace movement in East Germany.
Janisch, Wolfgang, 1940-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Wolfgang Janisch is a German photo collage artist and peace activist. Born in Berlin in 1940, Janisch’s early years were defined by the turmoil of life in post-war occupied Berlin. Living in East Berlin, Janisch often found himself ideologically at odds with the Soviet authorities, and his views are evidenced in his large body of work. Janisch specialized in photo collage and created hundreds of posters that satirically expressed his critical view of the Soviet government.
In addition to his work as an artist, Janisch worked for several publishing houses, including Dietz Verlag, Verlag Junge Welt, and Verlag Volk und Welt as a typesetter and designer of book jackets and cover pages. Janisch is also active in several organizations promoting the peace movement in Germany, including the Netzwerk Friedensteuer and the Mobile Friedensseminar.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Wolfgang Janisch papers consist primarily of his memoirs, photographic collages, other photographs, postcards, and correspondence related to political dissent and the peace movement in East Germany. A highlight of the Janisch papers is the significant collection of his original photographs, posters, and galleys of collages. The collection also includes documentation of Janisch’s persecution by the East German government through correspondence and police reports. The final theme of the papers is Janisch’s political activism in the peace movement in East Germany.
Germany (East)--Politics and government.; Art--Germany (East); Peace.; Dissenters--Germany (East); Civil rights--Germany (East); Germany--Politics and government--1990-; Audiotapes.; Video tapes.
- Biographical File, 1924-2000 (Boxes 1-5)
  - Memoirs: Ein Glas voll bunter Scherben
    - First manuscript (Box 1)
    - Second manuscript
    - Third manuscript (Box 2)
    - Final manuscript
    - Documents related to his memoirs
  - Short stories and poems (Box 3)
    - Short stories: Manuscript, 1998
    - Short stories: Opa’s kurze Geschichten, 1998
    - Poems: Manuscript, 1956-2000
    - Poems: Final manuscript: Opa’s poetische Erguesse, 2000
  - Personal documents (Box 4)
    - Passports, membership passes of FDGB
    - Certificates
    - Photocopies: Family and friends
    - Photocopies: Himself and his cats
    - Documents: Klaus Janisch: Occupation at theatre, 1958-1974
    - Correspondence: Klaus Janisch: Hospitalization, 1957-1983
    - Correspondence with medical authorities, 1977-1979
    - Documents: Klaus Janisch: Financial support, 1981-1984
    - Documents: Klaus Janisch: Drawings, 1980
    - Letters: Condolences: Walter Janisch, 1966
    - Letters: Condolences: Margarete Janisch, 1979
    - Receipts: Funeral home, 1966-1985
    - Correspondence: Klaus Janisch, Margarete Janisch, 1960-1971
    - Documents: Margarete Janisch, 1966-1979
    - Documents: Walter Janisch, 1924-1936
    - Family documents, miscellaneous
    - Correspondence: Helmut Gubitz, 1999-2000
    - Letters: Janisch to mother during military service, 1974-1975
    - Letters: Emma Wolf to Margarete Janisch, 1935-1960
    - Letters: Hermann Wolf, 1934-1944
    - Letters: Paul Wolf, 1941-1944
    - Letters: Miscellaneous
    - Documents: Miscellaneous
    - Pins and medals
  - Books related to his childhood (Box 5)
    - Der junge Naturforscher II (gift from his parents, 1952)
    - Der junge Naturforscher III, 1954
    - Der junge Naturforscher IV, 1956
    - Slides showing his family and friends
- Work at state-run East German publishing houses, 1961-1996 (Boxes 6-8)
  - 1961-1983 (Box 6)
    - Documents: Dietz-Verlag, 1961-1996
    - Certificates: Dietz-Verlag, 1964-1983
    - Dietz Verlag: Photographs of exhibition
    - Magazines: Simplidietzimus, in-house production of Dietz-Verlag
  - Books: Typography or cover art designed by Janisch
    - Deformierte Vergesellschaftung: Zur Soziologie des staatsmonopolistischen Kapitalismus der BRD. Akademie Verlag, Berlin, 1982
    - Das Haus am Laerchen Wald, two volumes, Jiří Křenek
    - Wahrhaftige Geschichten. Montesquieu
    - Artgerechte Jugendhaltung: Ideen zur selbständigen evangelischen Jugendarbeit in der Gemeinde. Timona-Verlag, Bochum, 1992
    - Buch Club 65, Heft 1. Berlin, 1977
    - Konrad’s Traktor. Kahlau, Heinz; Platzer Rudolf. Verlag Junge Welt, Berlin, 1974
    - Die grosse Initiative, V. I. Lenin. Dietz Verlag, Berlin, 1970
    - Lebendige Hoffnung, Evangelische Haupt-Bibelgesellschaft, Berlin, 1984
    - Die grosse Wende in einer kleinen Stadt. Becker, Franz. Dietz-Verlag, Berlin, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Anorganische Festköperreaktionen. Engels, Siegfried. Akademie-Verlag, Berlin, 1986, 1989
    - Surface Waves and Discontinuities. Malischewsky, Peter. Akademie-Verlag, Berlin, 1984
    - 10 sowjetdeutsche Erzähler. Verlag Volk und Welt, Berlin, 1982
    - Die Dolmetscherin. Gergely, Agnes
    - Litauische Poesie aus zwei Jahrhunderten. Verlag Volk und Welt, Berlin, 1983
    - Illustrierte Geschichte der deutschen frühbuergerlichen Revolution. Dietz-Verlag, Berlin, 1974
    - Internationale Buch-Ausstellung (iba), two volumes. Leipzig, 1971
    - Psychologie in unserem Leben
  - A series of books honoring the best designed books of each year (Box 8)
    Scope and Contents note
    Janisch is included in many of these volumes.
    - Die schönsten Bücher der DDR, 13 volumes, 1964-1983
- Work at the museum, 1995-2001 (Box 9)
  - Photographs: Work at museum
  - Work at museum: Letters, clippings, copies of guestbook, 1995-2001
- Political art, 1971-2003 (Boxes 9-20)
  - Collage: "Spielball" (Box 9)
  - Collage: "Wie man uns gerne hätte”
  - Collage: "Lebensfrohe, glückliche Leibeigene-unser Ziel"
  - Collage: "Die Deutschen Revolutionen"
  - Collage: "Golfregion"
  - Collage: "Den Opfern der Gewalt"
  - Collage: "Frieden ist möglich"
  - Collage: "Der grosse Kurfürst"
  - Collage: "Hurra! Gorbatschow fällt auf die Nase"
  - Collage: "Unmündig"
  - Collage: "Abteilungsleiter"
  - Collage: "Alles zum Wohle des Volkes"
  - Collage: "Nur Hammel laufen in der Herde"
  - Four untitled collages
  - Postcards designed by Janisch, 1971-1998
  - Rewards for collages, 1984-1998
  - Photocopies of collages, 1981-1989
  - Collages removed from exhibitions or prohibited, 1980-1989
  - Signets designed by Janisch, two offset plates used in production of two of Janisch’s posters
  - Newspaper clippings showing Janisch's collages, 1987-1991
  - Posters
    - Color posters, 92 images, 1983-1995 (Box 10)
    - 96 color posters and galley proofs, 1996-2000 (Box 11)
    - One galley proof of poster, "Ich will nicht so enden,", undated (Box 12)
    - 15 galley proofs of political posters, 1980s (Box 13)
    - 16 posters and 11 galley proofs (Box 14)
    - 30 galley proofs of posters (Box 15)
    - 37 galley proofs of posters (Box 16)
    - 84 posters about environmental concerns, peace, critique of consumer culture, militarism and German past in general, 1980s (Box 17)
    - 25 files, matted prints of animals, abstract images, galley prints (Box 18)
    - Newspapers from Germany, Netherlands, Denmark and England, 1966-1996 (Box 19)
  - Exhibition and related documents (Box 20)
    - List of exhibitions and collages donated
    - Correspondence: Exhibitions and related documents, 1982-1994
    - Clippings and related documents, 1995-1999
    - Invitations to exhibitions
    - Exhibitions in Netherlands: Documents, photographs, letters, 1984-2001
    - Exhibitions in Austria, Denmark, Canada: Clippings and related documents, 1987-2001
    - Photos of exhibitions
  - Janisch’s involvement in art organizations and events
    - Exhibition: "Fotomontage als Kunstprinzip" and related documents
    - Documents: "Künstlergruppe Blauer Reiter Leipzig,", 1989-1995
    - Postcards: "Bienale" in Mons (Belgium) and other artists, 1989-1995
- Political activities, 1981-2003 (Boxes 21-24)
  - Stasi and organizations for victims (Box 21)
    - Brochure: Abkürzungsverzeichnis/Häufig verwendete Abkürzungen und Begriffe des Ministeriums für Staatssicherheit. Berlin, 1996
    - Bruchure: Das Arbeitsgebiet in der Kriminalpolizei/Aufgaben, Strukturen und Verhältnis zum Ministerium für Staatssicherheit. Berlin, 1994
    - Correspondence: Buergerbuero, "Gesprächskreis politisch Verfolgter" and related documents, 1998-2001
    - Brochures: Torture victims, reports
    - Copies: Excerpts from Janisch’s Stasi files, 1986-1989
    - Newspapers: Stasi enlightenment, 1990-1991
    - Clippings, 1992-2002
    - Exhibition about the Stasi: Announcements and clippings, 1999-2001
    - Correspondence with German government, 2001
  - Involvement in peace organizations and related projects
    - Magazines and brochures about peace movements (Box 22)
    - Documents: "9th International Conference on War Tax Resistance and Peace Tax Campaigns,", 2002 September
    - Documents: "Netzwerk Friedenssteuer,", 1999-2003
    - Documents: "Das mobile Friedensseminar,", 1981-2001
    - Documents: Anti-war movements, 2001-2002
    - Newsletter: "Conscience of Canada,", 2000-2002
    - Newspapers: War on Iraq, 2002
    - Correspondence and publications of German parties and clippings about Iraqi War, 2001
    - Propaganda against war on Iraq, 2003
    - Book: Living Non-Violence: Ghandi in Action. Bharadwaj, A. B.; Delhi, 1988 (Box 23)
    - Brochures: Friedensmuseum der Evangelischen Kirche Berlin-Brandenburg: Seinen Ort finden, Ende und Anfang, 1997-1998
    - Brochure: Dem Frieden eine Chance geben!
    - Brochure: 10 Jahre nach der Revolution in der DDR/ Aufbruch 89. 3 issues, 1999-2000
    - Brochure: Für eine Zukunft in Solidarität und Gerechtigkeit. Kirchenamt der Evangelischen Kirche, 1997
    - Correspondence and material about exhibition: “Zur Kultur des Friedens,”, 2000
    - Book: Frieden...zur Kultur des Frieden, Eisenstadt, 2000
  - Material related to political work (Box 24)
    - Invitations and documents: Hanns-Seidel-Stiftung; August-Bebel-Institut, 2000-2001
    - Brochure: Gewaltfrei für Demokratie, 2000
    - Fremd im eigenen Haus. Rainer Eppelmann, with mentions of Janisch in text and Janisch’s annotations, 1993
    - Zu seinem Wort stehen. Friedrich Schorlemmer, 1994
      Memoirs of East German pastor, with copy of Janisch’s letter to him after publication.
    - Help-Report: "Fakten über drei Diktaturen" (HELP, e.V.), 1999
      Uses images of Janisch’s posters.
    - Verfassungen der DDR, 1990
    - Vom Grundgesetz zur Deutschen Verfassung, 1991
- Material revealing the time of the GDR, 1955-2002 (Box 24)
  - Atlas, 1955
  - GDR-jokes, 2000
  - Letter to the German “Bundestagspraesident,”, 1991
  - Clippings and related documents, 1990-2002
  - Miscellaneous documents
  - Videocasettes, sound cassettes, and disks
- Incremental material, 1940-2007 (Boxes 25-36)
  - Photography developing equipment, 1980s, undated (Boxes 25-28)
  - Praktika Nova camera, 1960s
  - Mienolta AF-EII camera, 1980s
  - Framed painting given to Janisch's parents by a Russian prisoner of war in thanks for their help, 1943 (Box 29)
  - Photography developing equipment, 1980s, undated
  - Biographical documents, 1940-2005 (Box 30)
  - Berlin Castle reconstruction printed matter, 2003-2005
  - Russian textbooks, 1947-1951
  - Peace activism printed matter, 2002-2005
  - Volk und Welt photographs, 1976 (Box 31)
  - Netzwerk Friedenssteuer printed matter, 1987-2006
  - Album of postcard reproductions of posters by Josef Huber, 1980s-1990s (Box 32)
  - Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1993-2006 (Box 33)
  - Deutsche Demokratische Republik reparations correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1993-2006
  - Personal correspondence and photographs, 1993-2005
  - Photographs of posters, 1977-1993, undated
  - Berlin Castle reconstruction printed matter, 1998-2006 (Box 34)
  - Berlin Castle reconstruction printed matter, 1998-2007 (Box 35)
  - Netzwerk Friedenssteuer printed matter, 2007
  - Political questionnaires, 1996, 2003 (Box 36)
  - Correspondence related to Janisch's artwork with various publishers, museums, and archives, circa 1980-2000
  - Meopta Axomat 4 enlarging apparatus (Memorabilia shelf)
  - "Vorwärts immer Rückwärts," art object, 1990s (Memorabilia shelf)